Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ernie O'Malley Papers
1643-2010
1920-1957
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
O'Malley, Cormac K. H.
O'Malley, Ernie, 1897-1957
AIA.060
40.5 Linear Feet in 27 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, and 12 oversize flat boxes.
Ernie O'Malley was an Irish Republican Army officer during the Irish War of Independence of 1919-1921 and a senior commander of the anti-treaty IRA during the Irish Civil War, 1922-1923. During the course of the war he was wounded, captured, and participated in a hunger strike. After the war he traveled in Europe and in the United States to raise funds for the Irish Press. O'Malley was a man of diverse intellectual and artistic interests, which led him to live in New Mexico and New York and travel in Mexico. He was married to American artist Helen Hooker in 1935, the two moved to Ireland, divorcing in 1952. O'Malley died in 1957. The collection contains manuscript works of Ernie O'Malley and other individuals; correspondence, both personal and business-related; finacial and legal records; materials concerning art and art-collecting; and nationalist material including military training manuals, diaries, clippings, and financial and legal material. Of special interest are drafts and publicity related to several of O'Malley's works including On Another Man's Wound, The Singing Flame (published in the United States as Army without Banners), Raids and Rallies, and several poems. Of note is correspondence between O'Malley and the artist Jack B. Yeats. Additional series contain materials collected by O'Malley and his son Cormac O'Malley.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 15 series. Files are arranged alphabetically except where noted.
Collection is arranged into 15 series, some of which are further arranged into subseries. Series are arranged either alphabetically or chronologically.
Missing Title
Series I. Works, 1924-1956, undated
Series II. Correspondence: Incoming, 1922-1956
Series III. Correspondence: Outgoing, 1922-1956
Series IV. Correspondence: Family, 1914-1957
Series V. Personal, 1912-2006
Series VI. Legal, 1921-1957
Series VII. Financial, 1935-1957
Series VIII. Nationalist Materials, 1643-1966, undated
Series IX. Jack B. Yeats, 1904-1980
Series X. Diaries, Notes and Research, 1922-1963
Series XI. Clippings and Publicity, 1895-2002
Series XII. Arts Material, 1918-1955
Series XIII. Chronology Files, 1920-1957
Series XIV. Subject Files, 1922-2008
Series XV. Printed Ephemera, 1789-1950
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Ernie O'Malley (1897-1957) was an Irish Republican Army officer during the Irish War of Independence of 1919-1921 and a senior commander of the anti-treaty IRA during the Irish Civil War, 1922-1923. O'Malley wrote four books, On Another Man's Wound, The Singing Flame, Raids and Rallies, Sean Connolly of Longford in addition to numerous poems, short stories, articles and reviews. A renaissance man, O'Malley was interested in art, archaeology, folklore, photography, literature and history, but also in the lives of those he fought with during the Irish Independence movement. In the 1950s he interviewed over 450 survivors of those he had fought along with, and these interviews were the basis for the episodes covered in his Raids and Rallies and Sean Connolly.
O'Malley was studying medicine at University College Dublin in 1916 when the Easter Rising took place. Although not a nationalist at the time, O'Malley having been invited by some friends to help defend Trinity College, Dublin in case the Irish Volunteers attempted to take it over, he decided his sympathies were with the rebels and thus began his military career. When he went on the run in 1917, he was asked by Michael Collins to organize IRA brigade units throughout rural Ireland and later as a Commandant General, at age 24, he commanded the IRA's Second Southern Division in Munster with 7,000 men. O'Malley was captured twice during his military career, the first time by the British in Kilkenny in December 1920 after which he was interrogated and badly beaten. With the threat of execution imminent he, and two other IRA men, escaped from Kilmainham Jail on February 14, 1921. At this arrest he had identified himself as 'Bernard Stewart' and when he escaped, his true identity was still unknown. O'Malley was captured a second time in the civil war on November 4, 1922 after a shoot-out with Free State troops in a house in Dublin. Critically wounded, he managed to survive prison for almost two years and 41 days on hunger strike before finally being released in July of 1924. Although still not well, he decided to seek a warmer climate hoping to recover both physically and spiritually and traveled in Europe spending time hiking in the Pyrenes, museum hopping and self-studying art and architecture while constantly writing. After returning to medical studies in Dublin for 1926-28, he was asked to go with Frank Aiken to the United States by Eamon de Valera to raise funds for the establishment of a new independent newspaper, The Irish Press. His notes and impressions of these journeys, 1928-1935, are included in the collection in Notebook Series and elsewhere in the Correspondence Series. O'Malley settled in Taos and Santa Fe, New Mexico for 1929-1932 and while there met many artists and writers and occasionally lectured on modern Irish history and literature while writing his memoirs. He also traveled extensively in Mexico in 1931 for nine months following his interests in folklore, archaeology, modern Mexican art and teaching, - all the while writing.
In 1932 during the height of the Depression, O'Malley returned to New York to finish and publish his memoir, On Another Man's Wound. With introductions from Paul Strand, met many of the city's literary, theatre and artistic circles. He continued to write articles, poems and short stories, but only his poems were published. The manuscript for his memoir was rejected many times. In the meantime with the change in government in Ireland, he became eligible for a pension for his military service and wounds, and this led to his return to Ireland to secure his pension. While in New York he also met his future wife here, Helen Hooker, a sculptor and photographer, who had travelled extensively in Europe and Russia. Helen was the daughter of Elon Huntington Hooker, a wealthy businessman and founder of Hooker Electrochemical Company from Greenwich, Connecticut. When he returned to Ireland in 1935 she followed him. They married on September 27, 1935, and he returned to medical school. The couple settled initially in Dublin and later in County Mayo, Ireland, on a farm. O'Malley continued writing and Helen continued her sculpture, photography and theatre interests. The couple had three children. After the marriage broke down in the late 1940s and Helen effectively returned to the United States, seized two of the children, Cathal and Etain, and brought then to America where she initiated divorce proceedings in 1950. O'Malley's youngest son, Cormac, remained with his father. The divorce was finalized in 1952. After being in poor health for several years Ernie O'Malley died in 1957 in Dublin.
During his lifetime, O'Malley published one critically acclaimed work about his experiences in the Irish War for Independence: On Another Man's Wound. His second volume, The Singing Flame, covering the Civil War was only published posthumously. O'Malley had published a series of articles in The Sunday Press in 1955-56 describing his and other fighters' experiences, using the interviews he had conducted with former IRA men. These were also published after his death as Raids and Rallies. The collection includes this serialization as well as reviews and publicity on these works and others in the Clippings and Publicity Series.
In 1991, Prisoners: The Civil War Letters of Ernie O'Malley was published by his son Cormac and Richard English, the latter who also went on to write his biography, Ernie O'Malley: IRA Intellectual in 1998. In 2007, Cormac edited and published No Surrender Here!The Civil War Papers of Ernie O'Malley, 1922-1924, being a compilation of anti-Treaty military communications and his father's letters from prison during the Civil War. Cormac also edited and published Rising-Out: Sean Connolly of Longford, 1890-1921 in 2007. Broken Landscapes: Selected Letters of Ernie O'Malley, 1924-1957, also co-edited by Cormac and Nicholas Allen was published in 2011.
Existence and Location of Originals
Collection contains photocopies of original documents held by other repositories. The location of some originals is unknown.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Related materials include:
James J. Comerford Papers AIA 010
Cormac O'Malley Papers AIA 019
Archives of Irish American Pamphlet Collection AIA 047
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the personal, intellectual, and artistic interests and activities of the Ernie O'Malley. Materials documenting his participating in the Irish War of Independence and the Irish Civil War include manuscript material, collected military manuals, and interviews conducted with other veterans. Art catalogs, clippings, research files, correspondence with other artists, and poetry appear throughout the collection, illustrating O'Malley's keen interest in art and literature. Essays, articles, poetry, short stories, drawings, and manuscripts of his major works comprise a large portion of the collection. Correspondence with colleagues, friends, and family also make up a significant part of the collection. Further records document the personal, legal, and financial aspects of O'Malley's life. Also included are materials collected by O'Malley and his son, Cormac O'Malley, related to Irish literature and history.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The collection was donated to Tamiment Library in December 2010 by Cormac O'Malley, son of Ernie O'Malley. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.092. An addition donation was received in July 2012. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2012.066 and 2012.089.
Manuscripts; Legal documents.; Ireland -- History -- Civil War, 1922-1923 -- Personal narratives.; Diaries; Irish newspapers.; Newspapers.; Clippings (information artifacts); Ireland -- History -- Civil War, 1922-1923.; Ireland -- History -- Easter Rising, 1916; Postcards.; Ireland -- History -- 20th century.; Revolutionaries -- Ireland.; Political prisoners -- Ireland.; Correspondence.; Writings (document genre); Taos Pueblo (N.M.); Poetry.; Account books; Autobiography (genre); Young, Ella, 1867-1956; Hone, Evie, 1894-1955; Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1879-1962; Le Brocquy, Louis, 1916-; Irish Republican Army; Strand, Paul, 1890-1976; Crane, Hart, 1899-1932; Roelofs, Helen Hooker O'Malley, 1905-1993; De Valera, Eamon, 1882-1975; Yeats, Jack Butler, 1871-1957
- Series I. Works, 1924-1956, undated
  Arrangement
  Material in Subseries IA is listed alphabetically by title or nature of work. Material in Subseries IB is listed by author and title of the work and organized alphabetically.
  Scope and Content Note
  The series contains two subseries. Subseries A. Ernie O'Malley comprises literary manuscripts, articles, book reviews, essays, short stories, poetry, notes, drawings and speeches written or created by Ernie O'Malley between the years of 1926 and 1956. Published and unpublished works, manuscript drafts, reprints and photocopies are represented. A considerable amount of O'Malley's works were written during his travels throughout the United States and Mexico between 1928 and 1935. A substantial portion of his literary output centers on his homeland, his military experiences during both the Irish War of Independence and Civil War, early Christian art in Ireland and Irish artists. Other works reflect his interest in art, poetry and a variety of other topics. Materials within the Works series are manuscript and/or typescript and are so indicated.
  Works by other authors are found in Subseries B. Other Writers. Throughout his life O'Malley collected ballads and poetry written by others. While most of these materials were either transcribed by O'Malley himself or typed for his personal reference or use, several of the items are clippings or printed materials sent to him by friends and colleagues. Poets within this series include both American and European poets such as Lascelles Abercrombie, Hart Crane, Emily Dickinson, Horace Gregory, James Joyce, Stanley Kunitz, Ezra Pound, Seamus O'Sullivan, John Millington Synge and numerous others. Additional works by others include articles, plays and essays sent to O'Malley for his consideration, review and comment.
  For additional materials relating to the works and literary output of Ernie O'Malley see Series 10: Diaries, Notebooks and Research.
  - Subseries IA. Ernie O'Malley
    - Index to Works, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Adventures of Sean and Seamus"; typed, fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "A Painter of His People", The Bell book review, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Admirals for a Day" short story, manuscript, 2 drafts, circa 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Against Fate" short story, second version, circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Artillery" short story, circa 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - "The Attack on Drangan, June 3, 1920", Radio Eireann transcript for February 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      General Note
      Later published in The Sunday Press in 1955-1956 and Raids and Rallies in 1979.
    - Autobiography, 1933-1948; typed, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Book Review: "Irish Art in the Early Christian Period," typed, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Book Review: "Shake Hands with the Devil", manuscript, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Book Review: "The Islander by Tomas O'Crohan," typed, circa 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Christian Art in Ancient Ireland" by Adolph Mahr; EOM annotations, manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Connaught; EOM notes on book, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Contemporary Mexican Influence in the Arts" essay, manuscript, typescript, published 1947, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "County Mayo" essay, manuscript draft, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "The Dark Girl" short story, 2 versions - manuscript and typescript, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Drawings: General, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 15A)
    - Drawings: pencil drawings near Taos, New Mexico, circa 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "The Ernie O'Malley Introduction, 1945" (regarding Jack B. Yeats; reprinted from Yeats Exhibition Catalog) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Hotel Lobby" manuscript, unpublished draft of short story, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Ireland, Introduction to" essay; published July 1947 in Architectural Design, photocopy (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Louis le Brocquy: typed draft of article, manuscript notes, and photocopy of article published in Horizon, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "Lower Part" short story, undated (Box 1, Folder 20A)
    - "Maire Cain" draft of short story, manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "My favorite gramophone records: Jaran to Tunis", EOM address to Radio Eirann, manuscript, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Nothing ever happens", draft short story, manuscript, circa 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook, 1918, circa 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 23A)
      Red hardbound science laboratory notebook containing medical school notes by student Thomas Brady and notes written by Ernie O'Malley.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook "A", circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23B)
      Brown notebook with original notes and writings on travel and experiences from 1918.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook "B", 1919 (Box 1, Folder 23C)
      Brown notebook with notes and original writings on travel.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook "D", 1920 (Box 1, Folder 23D)
      Brown notebook with notes and original writings concerning books read and Ernie O'Malley's experiences in Ireland during the 1919-1920 time period.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook "D", 1921 (Box 1, Folder 23E)
      Brown notebook containing notes and original writings by Ernie O'Malley, in addition to notes by M.E. Hughes on the relationship between France and England.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook "E", circa 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 23F)
      Blue notebook containing notes and original writings concerning the Irish Civil War.
    - On Another Man's Wound: handwritten notes, 1928-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23G)
      Loose handwritten notes by Ernie O'Malley in preparation for On Another Man's Wound, including descriptions of life as an Irish Volunteer and perceptions of them.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook: "Taken from 'F' Notebook", circa 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 23H)
      Loose handwritten notes from a notebook concerning the Irish Civil War and Ernie O'Malley's experiences in Taos, New Mexico.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook "G", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 23I)
      Orange notebook containing notes and writings concerning Ernie O'Malley's experiences in both Ireland and New Mexico.
    - On Another Man's Wound: handwritten notes, circa 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 23J)
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 23K)
      Brown notebook containing notes by M.E. Hughes on patriotism and original writings by Ernie O'Malley.
    - On Another Man's Wound: notebook, circa 1928-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23L)
      Brown notebook containing chronologies, early drafts of On Another Man's Wound, and a list of names from the 1916 time period.
    - "On Another Man's Wound", drafts and notes, manuscript and typescript with corrections, (fragile onionskin): I, circa 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "On Another Man's Wound", drafts and notes, manuscript and typescript, (fragile onionskin): II, circa 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-A], 1932-1934 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-B] (I), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-B] (II), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-B] (I), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-B] (II), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-B], 1934 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-B], 1934 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-C]: Chapters 1-11 (I), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-C]: Chapters 1-11 (II), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-C]: Chapters 12-22 (I), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-C]: Chapters 12-22 (II), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-C]: Chapters 12-22 (III), 1934 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - On Another Man's Wound: typescript [TS-C]: additions, circa 1934 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - "On Another Man's Wound": loose notes, manuscript, circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - On Another Man's Wound: page proofs with corrections (Chapter 15-end), 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 26A)
    - "Painting: The School of London" article, The Bell, Jun 1947 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Poetry and Irish translations notebook, circa 1928-1935, undate (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Notebook containing original poetry and translations of other Irish poems, including poetry by John macNeill, Douglas Hyde, David O'Breadain, Egan o'Rahilly, E Hall, Ossianic Poems, and John Eglington.
    - Poetry notebook, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Notebook includes notes on "The Return," a book review, and poetry by Ernie O'Malley, including "The Story of a Maiden Fair," "The First Year," and "Truth."
    - Poetry notebook, circa 1929-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Poetry notebook, circa 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Notebook contains 31 poems by Ernie O'Malley, including "Earth," "O soft-hued moon, I'd liek to walk a Dublin Street," "Connemara," "Waiting," "Couriers," "Embers," "Pale Silver Was Her Face," "Bootleg," "The Mountain Speaks," "The Swarthy Snow Looks Sullen," "Sea Depths," "Failure," "Freedom," "The Horse Pass Towards the Mountains," "This Broken Plinth of Bare Mud Wall," "Why by Captious," "On the Mountain Die the Snow Lies Deep." "Moonlight Song," "What Alchemy Assists You Distill," "Words," "Complication," "Desert House," and "Memory Why He Tyrannous."
    - Poetry: notes, list of poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Poems sent to Eileen MacCarville (Dublin) from New Mexico, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Poems include, "Full Moon," "Earth," "The Time of Day," "Plaza," "New Moon," "Mexican," "Moonlight Song: Taos," "Shalako: Zuni," "Drums: War Dance, Puye," and "The Middenlerof."
    - Poetry: photocopies: I, circa 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Poetry: photocopies: II, circa 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Poetry: photocopies: III, circa 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Poetry; drafts, manuscript, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Poetry, draft, first set, typescript, circa 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Poetry, Final, 51 poems, typescript, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Typed drafts of "final" set of 51 poems by Ernie O'Malley, including 10 signed. Poems include "Inspiration," "Couriers," "Vorticist," "We Have Not Sought for Beauty Being Wise," "Embers," in addition to numerous unpublished writings.
    - Poetry: lists by sets, typescript, circa 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Poetry: poems written in New Mexico, annotated, typescript, circa 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Poetry: Jan 7-Mar 7, drafts, manuscript (1929-1935?), undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "A", undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "B", undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "C", undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "D", undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "E", 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "F", 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "G", 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "H", undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "I", undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "J", undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "K", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "L", undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "M", 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "N", undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "P", undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "R", undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "S", undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "T", undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "U", undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "V", 1931 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "W", 1930-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "Y", undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set "Z", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Poetry: Alphabetical set: untitled works (titled by first line), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Raids and Rallies: drafts for Radio Eireann address in 1953, circa 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Raids and Rallies: research notes and drafts prepared for Radio Eireann address in 1953, circa 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Raids and Rallies: draft prepared for Radio Eireann address in 1953, circa 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Raids and Rallies: drafts prepared for Radio Eireann address, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6A)